<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="1" org="uniform" sample="complete"><milestone n="452" unit="card" />
<milestone ed="Magnus" n="Daphne." unit="tale" />
<milestone ed="More" n="DAPHNE AND PHOEBUS" unit="tale" />

<l n="tr"><placeName key="perseus,Daphne" authname="perseus,Daphne">Daphne</placeName>, the daughter of a River God</l>
<l n="tr">was first beloved by Phoebus, the great God</l>
<l n="tr">of glorious light. 'Twas not a cause of chance</l>
<l n="tr">but out of Cupid's vengeful spite that she</l>
<l n="tr">was fated to torment the lord of light.</l>
<l n="tr">For Phoebus, proud of Python's death, beheld</l>
<l n="tr">that impish god of Love upon a time</l>
<l n="tr">when he was bending his diminished bow,</l>
<l n="tr">and voicing his contempt in anger said;</l>

<l n="tr">“What, wanton boy, are mighty arms to thee,</l>
<l n="tr">great weapons suited to the needs of war?</l>
<l n="tr">The bow is only for the use of those</l>
<l n="tr">large deities of heaven whose strength may deal</l>
<l n="tr">wounds, mortal, to the savage beasts of prey;</l>
<l n="tr">and who courageous overcome their foes.—</l>
<l n="tr">it is a proper weapon to the use</l>
<l n="tr">of such as slew with arrows Python, huge,</l>
<l n="tr">whose pestilential carcase vast extent</l>
<l n="tr">covered. Content thee with the flames thy torch</l>
<l n="tr">enkindles (fires too subtle for my thought)</l>
<l n="tr">and leave to me the glory that is mine.”</l>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><l n="tr">to him, undaunted, Venus, son replied;</l>
<l n="tr">“O Phoebus, thou canst conquer all the world</l>
<l n="tr">with thy strong bow and arrows, but with this</l>
<l n="tr">small arrow I shall pierce thy vaunting breast!</l>
<l n="tr">And by the measure that thy might exceeds</l>
<l n="tr">the broken powers of thy defeated foes,</l>
<l n="tr">so is thy glory less than mine.” No more</l>
<l n="tr">he said, but with his wings expanded thence</l>
<l n="tr">flew lightly to <placeName key="tgn,7011022" authname="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName>, lofty peak.</l>
<l n="tr">There, from his quiver he plucked arrows twain,</l>
<l n="tr">most curiously wrought of different art;</l>
<l n="tr">one love exciting, one repelling love.</l>
<l n="tr">The dart of love was glittering, gold and sharp,</l>
<l n="tr">the other had a blunted tip of lead;</l>
<l n="tr">and with that dull lead dart he shot the Nymph,</l>
<l n="tr">but with the keen point of the golden dart</l>
<l n="tr">he pierced the bone and marrow of the God.</l>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><l n="tr">Immediately the one with love was filled,</l>
<l n="tr">the other, scouting at the thought of love,</l>
<l n="tr">rejoiced in the deep shadow of the woods,</l>
<l n="tr">and as the virgin Phoebe (who denies</l>
<l n="tr">the joys of love and loves the joys of chase)</l>
<l n="tr">a maiden's fillet bound her flowing hair,—</l>
<l n="tr">and her pure mind denied the love of man.</l>
<l n="tr">Beloved and wooed she wandered silent paths,</l>
<l n="tr">for never could her modesty endure</l>
<l n="tr">the glance of man or listen to his love.</l>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><l n="tr">Her grieving father spoke to her, “Alas,</l>
<l n="tr">my daughter, I have wished a son in law,</l>
<l n="tr">and now you owe a grandchild to the joy</l>
<l n="tr">of my old age.” But <placeName key="perseus,Daphne" authname="perseus,Daphne">Daphne</placeName> only hung</l>
<l n="tr">her head to hide her shame. The nuptial torch</l>
<l n="tr">seemed criminal to her. She even clung,</l>
<l n="tr">caressing, with her arms around his neck,</l>
<l n="tr">and pled, “My dearest father let me live</l>
<l n="tr">a virgin always, for remember Jove</l>
<l n="tr">did grant it to Diana at her birth.”</l>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><l n="tr">But though her father promised her desire,</l>
<l n="tr">her loveliness prevailed against their will;</l>
<l n="tr">for, Phoebus when he saw her waxed distraught,</l>
<l n="tr">and filled with wonder his sick fancy raised</l>
<l n="tr">delusive hopes, and his own oracles</l>
<l n="tr">deceived him.—As the stubble in the field</l>
<l n="tr">flares up, or as the stacked wheat is consumed</l>
<l n="tr">by flames, enkindled from a spark or torch</l>
<l n="tr">the chance pedestrian may neglect at dawn;</l>
<l n="tr">so was the bosom of the god consumed,</l>
<l n="tr">and so desire flamed in his stricken heart.</l>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><l n="tr">He saw her bright hair waving on her neck;—</l>
<l n="tr">“How beautiful if properly arranged! ”</l>
<l n="tr">He saw her eyes like stars of sparkling fire,</l>
<l n="tr">her lips for kissing sweetest, and her hands</l>
<l n="tr">and fingers and her arms; her shoulders white</l>
<l n="tr">as ivory;—and whatever was not seen</l>
<l n="tr">more beautiful must be.</l>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><l n="tr">Swift as the wind</l>
<l n="tr">from his pursuing feet the virgin fled,</l>
<l n="tr">and neither stopped nor heeded as he called;</l>
<l n="tr">“O Nymph! O <placeName key="perseus,Daphne" authname="perseus,Daphne">Daphne</placeName>! I entreat thee stay,</l>
<l n="tr">it is no enemy that follows thee—</l>
<l n="tr">why, so the lamb leaps from the raging wolf,</l>
<l n="tr">and from the lion runs the timid faun,</l>
<l n="tr">and from the eagle flies the trembling dove,</l>
<l n="tr">all hasten from their natural enemy</l>
<l n="tr">but I alone pursue for my dear love.</l>
<l n="tr">Alas, if thou shouldst fall and mar thy face,</l>
<l n="tr">or tear upon the bramble thy soft thighs,</l>
<l n="tr">or should I prove unwilling cause of pain!</l>

<l n="tr">“The wilderness is rough and dangerous,</l>
<l n="tr">and I beseech thee be more careful—I</l>
<l n="tr">will follow slowly.—Ask of whom thou wilt,</l>
<l n="tr">and thou shalt learn that I am not a churl—</l>
<l n="tr">I am no mountain dweller of rude caves,</l>
<l n="tr">nor clown compelled to watch the sheep and goats;</l>
<l n="tr">and neither canst thou know from whom thy feet</l>
<l n="tr">fly fearful, or thou wouldst not leave me thus.</l>

<l n="tr">“The Delphic Land, the Pataraean Realm,</l>
<l n="tr">Claros and <placeName key="perseus,Tenedos" authname="perseus,Tenedos">Tenedos</placeName> revere my name,</l>
<l n="tr">and my immortal sire is Jupiter.</l>
<l n="tr">The present, past and future are through me</l>
<l n="tr">in sacred oracles revealed to man,</l>
<l n="tr">and from my harp the harmonies of sound</l>
<l n="tr">are borrowed by their bards to praise the Gods.</l>
<l n="tr">My bow is certain, but a flaming shaft</l>
<l n="tr">surpassing mine has pierced my heart—</l>
<l n="tr">untouched before. The art of medicine</l>
<l n="tr">is my invention, and the power of herbs;</l>
<l n="tr">but though the world declare my useful works</l>
<l n="tr">there is no herb to medicate my wound,</l>
<l n="tr">and all the arts that save have failed their lord.,”</l>
</div1></body></text></TEI.2>